let's say
you understand what the middle way is
and you have clear reasoning
that the only reason you suffer
is because of your attitude
in regard to feelings
so that's clear to you and you've
reasoned it
in all ways and then you think
but is it is it the case that
my attitude is the cause of myself is it
really is that really true is the middle way
is that really true is the middle way
the way to free myself from that
suffering to end craving is it really the way
to end craving is it really the way
so you have a doubt
now what do you do because you don't you
you don't
there's no confirmation that yeah that
is
the middle this is the middle way that's
that's what you do
if you're still doubting it means you
don't have the middle way
you might have as the suitors would say
you might have had
like um intellectual grasp of it correct
grasp upon reasoning correct reasoning but
upon reasoning correct reasoning but
yeah if the doubt
still um
perverts the picture around so to speak
so if
if in face of doubt you know that is the
truth means you're beyond doubt like
you might try to doubt it it's not that
um that you're beyond doubt because you
refuse to allow doubt to arise no the
doubt the question came up is it
and you look at it and it's like yes it
is and each time data is it
yes it is because you've seen it for
yourself but if you have a doubt arising
it says
is it it's like well i don't know well
that's the word
so you don't stop doing it because you
doubt it you do it more
because you doubt it
and uh and yes that intellectual
reasoning that that intellectual grasp
of
it makes sense that the suffering is
rooted in my attitude not in the
feelings or in the world
yeah that is a kind of unnecessary
prerequisite having that intellectual grasp of what
having that intellectual grasp of what
the right view is gives you the
direction to develop the right view and
hence go beyond doubt
so how to go to beyond doubt so how to
go beyond doubt
is to get the the that intellectual
correct reasoning first and then
when you doubt it you allow that doubt
to rise and then why
why do you want to go beyond doubt
because it's unpleasant oh
so the pain of the doubt is not rooted
in doubt
it's rooted in your craving against it
which aligns itself with your
intellectual understanding of what the
right view is
craving is the root of suffering not
phenomena at the root of suffering
whether it's doubt or something more
physical doesn't matter that's not the
root of suffering
so through the pain of doubt you get to
see the four noble truths
for example or any pain for that matter
for any discomfort
it's comfort of sensory strain anxiety
that arises on a kind of
not using pleasures as the only means of
escape from the unpleasant theories and
feelings and so on so any form of displeasure
and so on so any form of displeasure
if you suffer an account of it you use
that to see that suffering is actually
the attitude
you use basically that to keep applying
your correctly reasoned intellectual
correctly reasoned intellectual
understanding of what the right view is
and that's like in the suttas it's found
a different bit like a dhamma nusari
they're not upon us yet but they have
understood the right view
but now they need to practice that
either arrive that they drive you
through dhamma nusari like a
through that intellectual reasoning of
the correct kind
or through faith like oh this is
absolutely certain that what the buddha
said must be true and now they're applying it
must be true and now they're applying it
so they still both still have to do the
work and that work is what takes you
beyond doubt
not takes you beyond ability to ask self
questions or to put
your own self into a question but it
takes you beyond ability
to doubt the right answer so when you
see the right answer you know it's the
right answer
and you can doubt it and you heavily
doubt it and the doubt can never pervert
that order
and put itself first because the right
answer now is established and seen
through and through
so how you go beyond doubt through like
repetition of understanding
sufficient repetition of understanding
so that's the thing
so intellectually you have the idea
correct but now you also need to apply that you
but now you also need to apply that you
have to do it with no
no result well exactly exactly
with the results will come in so that's
always that element of faith
in the same sense we said that before
you come and see the doctor
and based on your own reasoning and
knowledge that you acquired about the
you know your condition
you have a pretty safe bet that out of
all the doctors this
will probably be the right one makes
more sense
not just by reputation but even by what
you can understand that his medicine is
you see
well this is based on everything that i
know so far this is most likely going to
work or at least least likely to be wrong out
or at least least likely to be wrong out
of everything
but you still need to apply the medicine
because if you say yes he's right but
you're not applying medicine
makes no difference to your condition
because fundamentally the whole reason
you went to the doctor
is to cue yourself from your condition
of dukkha
so either way you have to apply it so
this doctor is the greatest why do you
think so i have no clue
okay well did you apply his teaching and
confirm that he's great no i haven't
well then your faith is useless and
meaningless but if your faith is like oh i have
but if your faith is like oh i have
faith that this is least likely to be
wrong and i know that based on the best of the
and i know that based on the best of the
basis of my experience of other doctors
and other applications and other
medicines okay so let me apply this and then i'll
okay so let me apply this and then i'll
verify if it's right or what's wrong if
i'm cured of duca or i'm not curious
okay you applied once and well exactly
the whole medicine tells you you need to
apply this for a sufficient amount of
time so
okay you don't apply it indefinitely for
the rest of my life without any
confirmation because the buddha himself
said if you do it rightly the results will
if you do it rightly the results will
have to come
so that's also a good criteria that you
can use
like for example if you are convinced
that this is the right doctor
yet here you are 20 years later
you're still subject to dukkha so is it
the right doctor though
have i been doing everything rightly
if so well then the instruction was not
right because i'm not free from this condition
because i'm not free from this condition
but sometimes people refuse to look that
and admire the doctor for the rest of
their life and they're still not cured
the only two reasons you won't be cured
either you're doing it wrongly the right
instruction or the instruction is not right and you
or the instruction is not right and you
must
basically investigate both if there are
no results sure
don't expect the results within one day
or five days or something
don't even expect it within a year
because most people's minds today are lazy and
most people's minds today are lazy and
driven to centrality so it's going to
take you a bit longer than that
but you know five years of doing
something it's like well
am i am i like you know free from doubt
free from suffering or not
how long will i keep this faith without
any verification going
maybe i need to reevaluate certain
things including the doctor
but see the problem with that is it gets
it gets harder to re-evaluate the doctor
if you spend more time invested in his
instruction because it feels like
the conclusion of my reevaluation might
be i have to start again
i don't want to start again well there
you go you just shot yourself in the
foot no you always have to be willing to
no you always have to be willing to
start again 30 years later
if you're not free from suffering if
you're free from suffering you know
there is no starting again this is it
this is the direction that just needs to
develop further
but if you still doubt that you're free
from suffering and are afraid to start
again practically what you are afraid of is to
practically what you are afraid of is to
practice because starting again
is part of the practice part of the
finding the right doctor
and then yes if you find the right
doctor first from suffering then you
might see in hindsight that all these
previous doctors they were not so right
actually did contribute towards your
right search so it was part of the same
progress but not if you decide you're not going
but not if you decide you're not going
to start again
that's it you remain stuck with the
wrong doctor out of fear to do the work
again you do want to get somewhere you want to
you do want to get somewhere you want to
be cured of the condition that's liable
to sickness aging and death i mean the
suitors cannot be more clear on that
so here we are practicing the buddhist
teaching seemingly without
donald you know all this is just just
another becoming becoming a sort of one
yes it's the right becoming
you use the right becoming to overcome
the wrong becoming and then arahant goes
beyond becoming
but if you said it's missing becoming
anything because you didn't you couldn't
do it
well basically you're not dismissing the
possibility of free of
freedom from suffering because why
wouldn't you want to become
free from suffering or becoming is bad
sure relatively speaking
but you can't just dismiss becoming of
any kind
while you're still subjected to these
unwholesome things and you don't know
the way out of suffering
that's it sounds like that's it's an
excuse it's just basically
becomes like that's what i mean like you
got stuck with your doctor now you feel
too old or too much invested time in
this direction to reevaluate to start
again it's just there's no way
that's where the longer you wait to
start questioning yourself rightly the
harder it will be because as the suttas
say you are accumulating a burden you know
you are accumulating a burden you know
papancha proliferation
it's an accumulation it's not a static
thing at any given time you just give it all
at any given time you just give it all
up no the more you've been engaging
with the attitude of not giving it up
the harder it will be to give it up
later on
so don't wait until that burden becomes
too much to give it up
and if you're doing things rightly there
has to be a result
again there's the symbol in the suit as
we refer to often
you know the the hands sitting on her on
her eggs even if she doesn't think
maybe may these chicks pierce out safely
through this shell they will because
she's doing the work
so if you are doing the work
you you you're kind of confident about
the middle way
you'll be on that but doubt is still
rising right fear is still arising last night
right fear is still arising last night
anger still arising
and then you think well that shouldn't
be the case i should have
i should know the truth
well you're not confident yeah you
you start by saying you're confident in
real way but then these things arise and
you doubt
and you think you shouldn't means you're
not confident middleweight if you're
confident in the middle way
you would know that these things would
still arise but you know the escape from
them you know what to do
you know where the problem is well
exactly exactly the problem with all of
those things you listed is that it makes
you feel
uncomfortable it makes you suffer it may
it causes uh painful feeling
and you know the escape in regard to
pain and feeling other than sensuality
other than giving it
now somebody who is coming in a way
might become
careless um lose the sense of urgency
content with knowing the escape
oh now i have confirmed that this is the
right doctor i already felt the
improvement but then i get killed as i go out expose
but then i get killed as i go out expose
the wound to the sun
or the dirt as the buddha would say and
you're not cured
although you know the way out you still
keep yourself sick through negligence
but sooner or later you have to address
it if you if you if
if a person truly has the right view
they cannot pretend
and ignore the problem for for well not
more than seven lifetimes as this would
say so that's the thing like uh you would
so that's the thing like uh you would
like for sotapana for example who is
obviously not free from sensuality
he can still have pressing desires he
might even give in to them out of
carelessness but fundamentally the pain of it is
but fundamentally the pain of it is
understood here well
the root of the pain is understood which
is your own craving
not not the sensuality not the beautiful
objects not the ugly objects not the
desire not the lack of desire the pain
is understood the escape from the pain
is understood
the origin and the way leading out of
and so on that's all understood
in other words you know exactly where
the problem is and by knowing where the
problem is you know how to solve the
problem but you do also know that it will take
but you do also know that it will take
time in the application and not becoming
negligent yeah because if you've been spending
yeah because if you've been spending
your whole life cultivating lust
or anger and then you've you know the
middle way
and okay you've confirmed it it's not
like the lust or the anger that you've
been of course
of course just know it yeah it will not
be it's already
significantly diminished so yes
a noble disciple who is not fully
enlightened yet can certainly still
experience central desire and anger but
to a degree
it's not like putin is anger and
putrugen essentiality and puthujan is
negligence because
it's it's like he doesn't know the way
up doesn't know the world to it
it's far worse it could only go so far
exactly yeah so knowing the way out
it's it's already like a a massive step
towards the escape and the buddha
himself said that
he said like gaining the right view the
amount of suffering that's left for
somebody with the right view it's like
seven grains of sand
and one without an eye view it's like
the mount sumero
and the sutras so that's like a gigantic
himalaya himalaya amount of suffering if you
himalaya amount of suffering if you
don't have the right view
just getting the right view diminishes
that to seven grains of sand
now the seven grains of sand is the
practice of sotapana to another hunt
lust arises luster rises ill will arises
and so on hindrances arise there's a
desire for pleasure
yeah there's a desire to avoid pain yeah
all basically all
like all all a noble disciple would have
to do is practice sense restraint
he wouldn't need to then be dealing with
a doubt as well
whether this is where because he knows
all he needs to do is not give in to
that impulse
towards uh lust or real will
or negligence all he needs to do is
abstain from the
impulse and that already results in
clarity of what's there
understanding of duke and so on so neca
masangkapa developed sufficiently in thoughts of
developed sufficiently in thoughts of
renunciation
are for somebody with the right view
and that's where the work is that's
what's all about enduring and so on
allowing things to endure that's already
the beginning of it but yeah
that doubt is always a tricky one isn't
it because
well yeah you feel like i must address
this but the point realizes well no the
only reason i want to address this
because i want to get rid of the pain of
it
not find the right answer because you
already know the right answer and that's
when when that doubt is sort of when people
when that doubt is sort of when people
like like well basically irrational
neurotically yeah but what if yeah but what if you
yeah but what if yeah but what if you
have a body and each time you provide
the right answer and you know it's the
right answer if you were not affected
emotionally by that doubt
if somebody were to ask you that same
question you would give the same answer
you know that is the truth
but your weakness is not lying it
doesn't lie in the fact that you don't
have the right answer lies in the fact
that you can't bear the pain
of the doubt so that's why none of the
answers can satisfy it because you're not really
can satisfy it because you're not really
answering for the sake of answer
you're answering it for the sake of not
feeling the pain and that doesn't work
you will feel the pain because you act
out of pain so your answer is you're
acting out of pain because i don't want
the pain
which means oh i need to endure the pain
not revolve around answering the doubt so if
revolve around answering the doubt so if
you endure the pain sufficiently
practice basically thoughts of
renunciation of your answering the doubt
refraining from it then oh this is the
escape of doubt
it's the escape of dukkha it's this type
of pain not
it's finding the right answer
that's rooted in not wanting the pain
so why do you don't want to pain no
because i don't know the way out of it
or because i do know the way out of it
but i'm just impatient and i want it to be
i'm just impatient and i want it to be
go away i don't have to deal with it
oh so you're not practicing rightly then
i want the pleasure of not having doubts
oh
well i want the pleasure of not having
pain the only reason doubt is a problem is
the only reason doubt is a problem is
because you don't want to deal with the
pain of it
that's it and that's by the way even in
mundane terms not just in terms of
dhamma and your
right view and soda party when people
when people's minds revolve around doubt
they revolve around it because of the
pain of it
not because of the not enough
information or clarity
in regard to the answer in the doubt
that's why doubt is a hindrance
because in that emotional let's see you
act for it because as if
it presents itself as if it needs an
answer for clarity but in reality it's
mask the problem is the pain and each time
the problem is the pain and each time
you try to give an answer all you do is
act out of not wanting pain and that's why
out of not wanting pain and that's why
pain will be there
because you're feeding it so endure the
doubt
what if my cheeks don't pierce what if
they do this what if i do that so you
stand up
so the chick the hen gets up sits goes
moves the eggs didn't
that's why the chicks will not appear
safely from the shell
from the eggs because out of her doubt
she keeps moving around and not sitting
on the eggs
but it doesn't matter if she doubts will
my chicks pierce will they not
what will happen to them if she doesn't
move on account of doubt
and induce it and keep sitting on the
cheeks they will piss out
and when she sees that once twice three
times doubt will become meaningless and you
doubt will become meaningless and you
won't be on doubt
because what if what if there's nobody
i've done this sufficiently enough that
i know what i need to do
for chicks to pierce out safely
but if she keeps fidgeting around and
moving she's actually not doing the work
on a kind of trying to fix the doubt and
deal with it and make sure that her
checks pass out safely ironically enough so i
pass out safely ironically enough so i
must find the answer in order to
practice rightly
and that's why i'm not practicing
rightly because i keep acting out of
pain of doubt
so that's what acting out of doubt is
always unwholesome
and even in in our venue rules acting
out of doubt is wrongdoing
even if what you did turned out not to
be against the rules
the fact that you acted out of doubt was
a minor breach of the rules
so if you doubt you don't do it even if
it might be
oh maybe maybe it would be the right
answer yeah but it's rooted in the doubt
which means my priority is not the right
answer it's not the creative understanding my
it's not the creative understanding my
priority is getting rid of the
discomfort of the doubt
and that's wrong you